{"tossups": [{"question": "This battle ended an invasion whose leader, seeking revenge for the Ionian Revolt, had an assistant constantly tell him \u201cMaster, remember the Athenians.\u201d Datis and Artaphernes were the losing commanders at this battle, which frustrated Darius the Great. News of this battle was swiftly delivered to Athens via Pheidippides [fuh-dip-ih-dees], a runner. For ten points, name this Greek victory, commemorated today with a 26 mile run.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Marathon</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "After tackling and beating a man named Wesley, this figure quipped \u201cSorry I had a fight in the middle of your Black Panther meeting.\u201d After a Viet Cong bombing, this man rescued Lieutenant Dan and Bubba, acting against his girlfriend Jenny\u2019s advice to \u201crun.\u201d The advice \u201clife is like a box of chocolates\u201d is given by the mother of, for ten points, what 1994 film character, played by Tom Hanks, who inexplicably experiences much of 20th century American history?", "answer": "<b> Forrest Gump</b> (accept either or both)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "Objects undergoing this process were sometimes dried out using the chemical natron or naturally by extreme cold. The byproducts of one stage of this process were often stored in canopic jars decorated with animals like jackals and baboons. Anubis was the god of this technique, which involves a final step of wrapping in linen bandages. For ten points, name this type of embalming that was common for pharaohs of ancient Egypt.", "answer": "<b> mummification</b> (accept descriptions like \u201c<b>creating mummies</b>\u201d)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This president affirmed the right to intervene in South American relations in his namesake corollary and sent the Great White Fleet around the world to showcase American naval power. This man, who claimed to \u201cspeak softly and carry a big stick,\u201d broke with William Taft, and ran in the election of 1912 with the Bull Moose party. For ten points, name this early 20th century president who appears with Lincoln, Jefferson, and Washington on Mount Rushmore.", "answer": "<b> T</b>heodore<b> Roosevelt</b> (accept<b> T</b>eddy<b> Roosevelt</b>; prompt on Roosevelt)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1995, this organization\u2019s LEAR created the nine atoms of anti-hydrogen, the first true antimatter. This group\u2019s AWAKE plasma experiment uses equipment and space once dedicated to the \u201cNeutrinos to Gran Sasso\u201d project. In 2012, scientists with this organization announced experimental data suggesting the finding of the Higgs boson. For ten points, name this research organization, based near Geneva, that operates the Large Hadron Collier.", "answer": "<b> CERN</b> (or the<b> European Organization for Nuclear Research</b> or the<b> Organisation europ\u00b4een pour la Recherche Nucl\u00b4eaire</b>)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "During this battle, Davy Gam died while leading a band of knights in defense of his monarch. This battle was preceded by a lengthy siege of Harfleur. During this battle, the English used stakes to protect their archers from opposing cavalry and used longbows to devastating effect as the French cavalry trudged through a muddy battlefield. For ten points, name this victory for Henry V during the Hundred Years\u2019War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Agincourt</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This country lost a rubber-producing territory to its northern neighbor with the Treaty of Petropolis. This country\u2019s highest point is the extinct volcano Nevado Sajama. This former owner of the State of Acre was the site of a Spanish colonial mint near the silver mines of Potosi, and it lost much of the Gran Chaco in a war with Paraguay. For ten points, name this \u201cplurinational\u201d country in South America that shares Lake Titicaca with Peru and whose two capitals are Sucre and La Paz.", "answer": "Plurinational State of<b> Bolivia</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this politician from Georgia who failed to win the Republican nomination for President in 2012 and served as Speaker of the House from 1995 to 1999.", "answer": "Newt<b> Gingrich</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A senator from this state was killed in a plane crash eleven days before the 2002 election, after which Norm Coleman became the most recent Republican to win a Senate seat from this state. Paul Wellstone served in this state\u2019s (+) Democratic-Farmer-Labor party, which replaced him on the 2002 ballot with Walter Mondale. Mark Dayton is the current governor of, and (*) </b> Amy Klobuchar and Al Franken are the current senators from, for ten points, what U.S. state where Coleman had served as mayor of St. Paul?", "answer": "<b> Minnesota</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this city, an author hired massive crowds to attend the premiere of his play</b><em><b> Hernani</b></em> <b>to avoid censorship. An 1862 novel contains a lengthy digression on this city\u2019s (+)</b> <b>sewer</b> <b>system. In two scenes set in this city, Javert [zha-vair] commits suicide by jumping into a river, and Marius is dragged from the (*) </b> barricades during the 1830 July Revolution by Jean Valjean. Several scenes in<em> Les Mis\u00b4erables</em> [lay miz-er-ahb] are set in, for ten points, what capital city of France?", "answer": "<b> Paris</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This leader defeated his rival Zwide [zwee-day] at the Battles of Mhlatuze [m\u2019lah-too-zay] River and Gqokli Hill. Henry Francis Fynn was given special access to Natal after treating</b> <b>this man. This ruler\u2019s downfall at the hands of his half-brother (+)</b> <b>Dingane [din-gah-nay]</b> <b>was assured after he caused a famine in the wake of his mother Nandi\u2019s death. This man\u2019s military accomplishments included the implementation of the (*) </b> iklwa spears and \u201cbuffalo horn\u201d formation. For ten points, name this founder of the Zulu kingdom.", "answer": "<b> Shaka</b> Zulu (or<b> Shaka</b> kaSenzangakhona)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}